Guide to the John William Grantham papers, 1822-1924 and undated, bulk 1866-1873
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
John William Grantham papers 1822-1924 and undated, bulk 1866-1873
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Grantham, John William, d. 1897.
3.0 Linear Feet 1,952 Items
Businessman, land owner, and state legislator, of Middleway, West Virginia.
Personal, family, and business papers, the majority concerning the operation of a country store by Grantham and James W. League. Includes papers relating to Grantham's local agency for the Arlington Mutual Life Insurance Co., and to his political career as a member of the newly-formed state of West Virginia legislature, 1872-1881. Collection includes daybooks, memorandum books, and a two volumes of House bills in the West Virginia legislature, 1872-1873.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Grantham papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1946.
Biographical Note
John William Grantham was born in Jefferson County, Virginia, around 1820, an area that would become part of West Virginia. He was a landowner, residing in a large brick mansion in Middleway, West Virginia by 1880. He married Phebe Phidelia Larue and had five children. In addition to serving as House legislator for the newly-formed state of West Virginia from 1872-1881, he also seems to have been the President of the Bank of Charlestown, W. Va., and owned both a mercantile store and a life insurance agency. He is reported to have died in Middleway, Jefferson County, Nov. 16 1887 rather than 1897, and is buried in the Episcopal and Masonic Cemetery in Middleway. Source: genealogy web sites.
Collection Overview
Personal, family, and business papers, the majority dating from 1866-1873 and concerning the operation of a country store by Grantham and James W. League. Includes papers relating to Grantham's local agency for the Arlington Mutual Life Insurance Co., and records pertaining to his political career as a member of the West Virginia legislature.
The correspondence and other manuscripts consist of ten letters concerning the political career of Grantham, a member of the newly-formed state of West Virginia legislature; a petition, 1872, against removal of the capital from Charleston to Wheeling; business papers of a country store run by Grantham and James W. League, 1850-1890; papers concerning Grantham's agency for the Arlington Mutual Life Insurance Co., of Charlottesville, Virginia, 1870s; family letters; and a circular letter, 1871, from Hudson Wood & Co., purchasing agents in New York, offering Grantham a chance to join in a counterfeiting scheme.
Bound volumes include check stubs, 1856-1858, 1 volume; daybooks, 1850, 1854-1860, 2 volumes, one partly used as a scrapbook; House bills of the West Virginia legislature, 1872-1873, 2 volumes; and memorandum books from Grantham's mercantile business, 1871-1875, 1879-1887, 7 volumes.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Grantham, John, d. 1897
League, James W.
Arlington Mutual Life Insurance Company of Virginia
Life insurance agents -- West Virginia
Legislators -- West Virginia
Merchants -- West Virginia
Middleway (W. Va.)--History
West Virginia -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950
Scrapbooks
Contents of Collection
- John William Grantham papers, 1822-1924 and undated, (4 boxes)
  - Correspondence and Financial Papers
    Includes both foldered manuscripts and small bound volumes.
    - 1822-1867 (Box 1)
    - 1868-1871 (Box 2)
    - 1871-1875
    - 1876-1924 and undated (Box 4)
  - Other Bound Volumes
    - Check stubs (Middleway, Va.), 1856-1858 (Volume S:1446)
    - Day book (Middleway, Va.), 1850 (Volume M:1447)
    - Day book (Middleway, Va.), 1854-1860 (Volume M:1448)
    - Memorandum book (Middleway, Va.), 1871 (Volume S:1451)
    - Memorandum book (Middleway, Va.), 1871 (Volume S:1452)
    - Memorandum book (Middleway, Va.), 1871 (Volume S:1453)
    - Memorandum book (Middleway, Va.), 1872 (Volume S:1454)
    - Memorandum book (Middleway, Va.), 1872-1875 (Volume S:1455)
    - Memorandum book (Middleway, Va.), 1879-1887 (Volume S:1456)
    - Memorandum book (Middleway, Va.), undated (Volume S:1457)